Mansfield French Papers
Mansfield French Papers
1893-1952
French, Mansfield Joseph, b. 1872.
2.25 linear ft.
Papers of the American civil engineer and New York historian.
2592811
Biographical History
Mansfield Joseph French (1872-1953) was born in New York City, the son of the merchant and manufacturer Joseph French and his wife Elizabeth Hull Smith. After finishing his public school education at Central High School in Syracuse, New York, French entered Syracuse University and graduated in 1894 as a civil engineer. While at SU he was active in Delta Kappa Epsilon fraternity (author Stephen Crane was also a member during his brief time at SU).
Association with several transportation companies during his professional career, French developed steady private interest in local history and genealogy. In 1934 he authored a short article for the SU alumni magazine on Stephen Crane. Another article concerned Champlain's attack on the Onondaga tribe in central New York (1948), while a third was titled "Ancestors and descendants of Samuel French the Joiner of Stratford, Connecticut" (1943). As an active life member of the Onondaga Historical Association, French served as its director and vice-president.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Mansfield French Papers are divided into two parts. Subjects contains research notes, correspondence and printed materials. Civil engineering records consists almost exclusively of specifications and blueprints for a number of transportation companies. These concentrate most heavily on the Oneida Railway Company, Syracuse Rapid Transit Company, and the Utica and Mohawk River Railroad. The drawings include grades, switches, crossings, and other related railway structures. There are no building plans.
Correspondents and subjects of local interest include P. Schuyler Miller, W. M. Beauchamp, A. C. Flick, Crandall Melvin, T. Aaron Levy, Lester G. Wells, William P. Tolley, Charles C. Noble, Stephen Crane, Delta Kappa Epsilon fraternity, Bishop Frederick T. Keeney, Reverend Ebenezer White, and Cyrenius Hall.
Arrangement of the Collection
Both series are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Architects; Historians; New York State; Railroads; Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900.; Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895.; French, Mansfield Joseph, b. 1872.; Syracuse University.; Civil engineering -- United States -- New York (State); Electric railroads.; Railroad engineering -- United States -- New York (State); Genealogy -- New York (State); Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Blueprints (reprographic copies); Mechanical drawings.; Civil engineers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Subjects
  - Castle, Marion, 1951; correspondence (Box 1)
  - Champlain, 1949-1952; correspondence (Box 1)
  - Cosmic energy, 1887-1952; undated; printed material (Box 1)
  - Crane, Stephen, 1926; 1952-1953; correspondence (Box 1)
  - D, 1871-1950; undated (Box 1)
  - Douglass, Frederick, 1952; notes (Box 1)
    See also Fayette Park
  - E, 1911; 1940-1952; includes Edwards Brothers Inc. (Box 1)
  - F, 1929-1938; includes Flick, A. C. and First Church Chronicle v.1 no.4 - v.1 no.7; correspondence, printed material (Box 1)
  - Fayette Park, 1952; undated; notes and printed material (Box 1)
    See also Douglass, Frederick and Loguen, Jermaine
  - French, Mansfield, 1893; letters from Europe (Box 1)
  - French family (Box 1)
  - French photo groups, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Geddes, James, 1805; map - gaol limits for Onondaga County (Box 1)
  - Hall, Cyrenius, genealogical correspondence (Box 1)
  - Hayes, Stanley W., 1944-1952; correspondence (Box 1)
  - Institute of American Genealogy, 1941-1942; undated (Box 1)
  - Jeshuan Prayer, 1949-1952 (Box 1)
  - Keeney, Frederick T. (Bishop, Methodist Church), 1918-1950; correspondence (Box 1)
  - L (Box 1)
  - Lansing, Henry H., 1902; correspondence (Box 1)
  - League of Nations, 1945-1950 (Box 1)
  - Levenworth family, Syracuse, NY, 1950; printed material (Box 2)
  - Levy, T. Aaron, 1947-1951 (Box 2)
  - Loguen, Jermaine Wesley, See Douglass, Frederick; Fayette Park
  - M (Box 2)
  - Methodist, 1939-1947; printed material (Box 2)
  - Miller, Frank J., 1898-1930; 1939,; 1942; correspondence, obituary (Box 2)
  - N (Box 2)
  - O (Box 2)
  - Onondaga Historical Association, 1932-1950; undated (Box 3)
  - P, 1932-1952 (Box 3)
  - Paragon Plaster Co., Syracuse, NY, 1908-1909 (Box 3)
  - R (Box 3)
  - Radcliffe, Lynn J., 1940-1944; undated (Box 3)
  - Religious notes, 1934-1952 (Box 3)
  - Robinson, T. Ralph, 1941; 1947; correspondence, printed material (Box 3)
  - S - Smith (Box 3)
  - S.A.R. [Sons of the American Revolution] - M.J. French (Box 3)
  - Syracuse, High School, 1922 (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University, 1942-1953 (Box 3)
  - U. S. etc (Box 3)
  - V (Box 3)
  - W (Box 3)
  - White, Ebenezer (Reverend), genealogical correspondence (Box 3)
  - World War II, printed material (Box 3)
- Civil engineering records
  - Brewer switch-point protector, pat. 1904 (Box 4)
  - Cleveland Electric Railway Company, undated; general track map (Box 4)
  - Cleveland Frog and Crossing Company, undated; miscellaneous blueprints (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous blueprints, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous documents, circa 1896-1906; undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets (Box 4)
  - New Orleans Railway Company, undated; Wharton manganese steel railroad crossing (Box 4)
  - New York Central & Hudson River Railroad, miscellaneous blueprints and specifications (Box 4)
  - Oneida Railway Company, miscellaneous blueprints; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Pennsylvania Steel Company, miscellaneous blueprints (Box 4)
  - Seneca Turnpike, Syracuse, NY, undated; T-rail centrepole construction (Box 4)
  - Syracuse and Eastside Railway Company
    - Minoa extension, plan and profile, undated (Box 4)
    - Coffer dam bulkhead, iron pier, undated (Box 4)
  - Syracuse Rapid Tranit Company
    - Miscellaneous printed material, 1897-1911; undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous blueprints, undated (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous blueprints, undated (Box 4)
  - Utica, NY, 1904; map (Box 4)
  - Utica and Mohawk Valley Railroad
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and specifications, 1895; 1905,; undated (Box 4)
    - "Utica and Mohawk Valley Railway," Street Railway Review, October 20, 1903 (reprint), 15 pp. (Box 4)
    - "Steel tie and concrete construction," Street Railway Review, October 12, 1907 (reprint), 8 pp. (Box 4)
    - "Thermite rail welding", circa 1907; drafts and typescripts (Box 4)
    - "Electric railway track construction", May 23, 1912; pencil mss., read at Syracuse University Engineers Club; 17 pp. (Box 4)
    - Rules of the Operating Department, 1910; General Rules for Conductors and Motormen, 1903, 17 pp. (Box 4)
  - Wharton Company, miscellaneous blueprints (Box 4)